<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://GonsalgeAlmeida.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://GonsalgeAlmeida.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2019-01-27T22:05:11-05:00</updated><id>https://GonsalgeAlmeida.github.io/</id><title type="html">Gonsalge Almeida</title><subtitle></subtitle><author><name>Gonsalge Almeida</name><email>gsnperera@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Daily Routine of The Data Incubator</title><link href="https://GonsalgeAlmeida.github.io/2023/01/9/Daily-Routine-of-TDI/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Daily Routine of The Data Incubator" /><published>2023-06-30T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-07-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://GonsalgeAlmeida.github.io/2018/01/15/Daily-Routine-of-TDI</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://GonsalgeAlmeida.github.io/2023/01/9/Daily-Routine-of-TDI/">&lt;p&gt;When I began applying for The Data Incubator, I wasn’t sure what I was getting into. All I knew was
that I wanted to be as skilled a data scientist as possible and TDI was a well respected training program.
Overall, the program has been even better than I had anticipated. The program is relies heavily on 
collaboration with the other members of the cohort. There are only a few scheduled events each day;
the rest of the time is unstructured with only a framework of each week’s miniproject being offered as
a guide. Everything else is learning from the other members of the cohort and the instructors on a more
personal, one on one level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;first-lecture&quot;&gt;First: Lecture&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day starts at 9:00am with a lecture. Each week, a different instructor is lecturing on a new aspect of 
data Engineering: Data wrangling, advanced machine learning, sql, spark, cloud processing architecture, etc. The lecture lasts one hour and usually 
goes through one or two prepared jupyter notebooks on specific topics of the week’s theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;second-coding-challenge&quot;&gt;Second: Coding Challenge&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Immediately after lecture, a hackerrank coding challenge is sent out. Sometimes these are completed individually,
usually with collaboration, and other times these are completed in pairs. I have found the partner coding to be especially helpful–
people often develop different techniques that they default to, so partner coding can force you out of your comfortable
habits and help you learn new methods. For example, when I was coding with my friend Vitya on a challenge, I wanted to use
an elegant method that would give us the result without needing to go through the weeds of the problem, and he wanted to 
take a brute force approach. After talking it over, we decided that my idea would fail given a specific input and that his idea
would result in runtime errors. By finding middle ground between the two, we were able to successfully solve the challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;third-answer-review&quot;&gt;Third: Answer Review&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an unofficial part of the schedule, but after the coding challenge ends, most of the cohort goes over the 
provided solution to the problem. Sometimes that is a short event because either the instructors’ solution matches
yours or they will have one or two things different that you can easily understand and see how they were implemented.
However, other times, this takes much longer– often the instructors’ will take a very abstract approach to solving
these problems in the interest of decreasing computation time. In either event, going over the solutions is a very useful
training technique, and I feel that my coding abilities have increased exponentially throughout the program in large 
part due to these collaborative challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fourth-unstructured&quot;&gt;Fourth: Unstructured&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of the day is unstructured. On a given day, most members of the cohort will be using this time to work
on the week’s mini-project while a few will be working on their capstone project. There is a lot of collaboration during
this time, and I have learned an incredible amount from the other members of my cohort (I hope they can say the same).
The mini-projects are usually more focused on real world applications than the coding challenges. We are provided with
unclean data, data structured in a manner not conducive to what we need, or, in some cases, no data at all and we have
to write scripts to scrape the data from websites. These projects are certainly also useful in building up my programming 
skills, but they are also instrumental in teaching us how to think and code like industry data scientists; we are given
many things to work on at once using realistic datasets to solve real-world problems with hard deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The capstone project is a single project designed by each participant which is built throughout the full length of the 
course. In actuality, it seems that most of the cohort puts more emphasis on the mini-projects and coding training than
the capstone because everyone has designed research projects previously and would prefer to learn as much new information
as possible via the other aspects of the program. The capstone is more meant to demonstrate to recruiters the participant’s
ability to design and complete a data science project largely independently than to be a particularly efficient learning method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;intermittent-partner-panels&quot;&gt;Intermittent: Partner Panels&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every couple of days, the cohort attends a partner panel. This is where a few hiring managers of some companies partnered with
The Data Incubator tell us a bit about their companies, explain what they’re looking for in a data scientist, and then answer
any questions from the participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;last-wrap-up&quot;&gt;Last: Wrap-up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of each day, the cohort gathers in a circle for a wrap-up session. Everyone discusses what they’ve learned that day,
what they’ve been working on, and what they are stuck on. In academia, there is a common trend that people feel like they are not
as qualified as their colleagues. I feel like this wrap-up has been very useful to everyone because with everyone being honest about
what they’re working on and what they’re struggling with, it shows us that everyone is struggling to learn something. The wrap-up helps
prevent anyone from feeling like they aren’t good enough because they are struggling and helps build a sense of comradarie among the
participants because we are all working to improve ourselves as data scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy the routine and methodology of The Data Incubator. While there is a bit of structure in the lectures and the guidelines for the
mini-project, the overall mentality is that we are all self-driven individuals here to learn as much as we can. Because of that, the
instructors do not over-regulate our time in the program– this has been useful for us because it allows us to focus more on what we
most need to improve. That and the collaborative nature of the program has really helped me improve my abilities as a data scientist/statistician.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Gonsalge Almeida</name><email>gsnperera@gmail.com</email></author><category term="tdi" /><category term="coding" /><summary type="html">When I began applying for The Data Incubator, I wasn’t sure what I was getting into. All I knew was that I wanted to be as skilled a data scientist as possible and TDI was a well respected training program. Overall, the program has been even better than I had anticipated. The program is relies heavily on collaboration with the other members of the cohort. There are only a few scheduled events each day; the rest of the time is unstructured with only a framework of each week’s miniproject being offered as a guide. Everything else is learning from the other members of the cohort and the instructors on a more personal, one on one level.</summary></entry></feed>
